<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two essays of love and marriage being a letter written by a gentleman to his friend, to disswade him from love and an answer thereunto by another gentleman, together with some characters and other passages of wit / written by private gentlemen for recreation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H84</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12157874</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12157874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 599:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two essays of love and marriage being a letter written by a gentleman to his friend, to disswade him from love and an answer thereunto by another gentleman, together with some characters and other passages of wit / written by private gentlemen for recreation.</title>
                  <author>J. H.</author>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 123 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First letter signed: J.H.; second signed: A.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love.</term>
               <term>Marriage.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two Eſſays of LOVE AND MARRIAGE. Being A LETTER Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by a Gentleman to his Friend, to diſſwade him from Love. And an ANSWER thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by another Gentleman. Together with ſome Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters and other Paſſages of Wit. <hi>Written by Private Gentlemen for recreation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Si <hi>quando gravabere curis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Haec lege, pro moeſtae medicamine mentis He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beto.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Hand</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:2"/>
            <head>THE STATIONER To the READERS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentl:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe ſcattered Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers coming to my hands, I thought fit upon good Reaſons, to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate them to you. I might tell you they are delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:55195:3"/> and ingenuous; but you will not take me for a competent Judge, being neither learned, nor indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; <hi>Laudat venales—</hi>The truth is, my aim is as the <hi>Scots</hi> was, <hi>for all your geuds,</hi> And to pleaſe you, and profit my ſelf, is the ambition and deſign of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant, <hi>H. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55195:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55195:4"/>
            <head>To his honoured Friend on his being in love.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>True Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BUt that I know <hi>hereſie</hi> is faſhionable, and <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> the time-Livery, thou wouldſt force me to no little wonder, which way poſſible thou ſhouldſt ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into <hi>Love,</hi> be ſick and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh in <hi>Love,</hi> loſt as well to <hi>reaſon</hi> as good <hi>company,</hi> lockt up from all the World but thy own thoughts, and onely converſant with thy ſelf; yet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55195:5"/> formerly pleaſant and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, deſirous and deſired of Society, and one that I know has lived no <hi>Anchorite</hi> upon Earth; nor yet haſt had thine eyes tied up to any one face, but haſt both viewd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſt with variety of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> nay, I dare ſay, not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ignorance of more: yet that after ſo many <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes,</hi> thou ſhouldſt be ſo far fallen from thy primitive goodneſs, as to loſe thy ſelf in <hi>dotage,</hi> and that dotage on one <hi>creature,</hi> and that creature a <hi>woman,</hi> and call it <hi>Love</hi> too, really next to a miracle, is my onely admiration. Prethee do not miſcall thy diſeaſe,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55195:5"/> and be ſick of <hi>luſt,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of Love; I can never believe that that noble paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can be the ruine of its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; neither will I ſo much diſparage it, as to make a <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> its object. If there be love, tis to <hi>Heaven,</hi> Vertue, thy Countrey, Parents, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Friends, or what is of worth: but to the femall Sex, and in thy ſenſe where ſenſuality cannot but have an intereſt, though licenc'd by an Ordinance, 'tis onely Love ſcandall'd, it being (to the pity of the poor paſſion I ſpeak it) but concupiſcenſe handſomly burniſht, or a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appetite ſpeciouſly in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55195:6"/> And therefore could I never win my judgement to affirm, that the moſt eager of ſinners were in love with ſin, but onely temptingly ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a vicious doting; they did rather erroneouſly affect, then truly love. But let me inquire into thy paſſion: what, is it from the paint of nature, thoſe beautifull flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of red and white? me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks thou ſhouldſt as well be enamoured with thy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris's picture as her body; for even that too is not excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from art, and may be the worſt drawn. <hi>Frank,</hi> he that marries for a face, marries for a year; 'tis not a Summer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55195:6"/> ſince thy deſires wrought as ſtrongly upon Miſtris <hi>M. R.</hi> as now on this, and may be on as good a cauſe; yet how ſoon did a little diſeaſe wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both her beauty, and thy love? and I hope thou haſt not indented either with ſickneſs or time for this. Canſt thou be ſo prodigall of thy affection as to waſte it on ſuch incertainties? binde up thy ſelf to love for an age, when the cauſe of that love may periſh in a moneth? But I tell thee <hi>Frank,</hi> beauty is a Chimera, and has no being in nature: Every man makes his own Miſtris, and juſt ſo much luſtre do's he finde in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55195:7"/> her, as firſt his fancy gives her. For I dare challenge thee to ſhew me but one face in the whole world, that all opinions will give in for beautifull; ſo that Lovers, as thou call'ſt them, are but in the number of Pagans; they but worſhip that Idoll which themſelvs have made. May be thou wilt tell me of manners, carriage, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; I am very glad to hear of it; but let not thy paſſion hang in thy eyes when thou lookſt on them; for many of them, their geſtures are but School-poſtures, and ſeem rather like a motion then a carriage. Conſider that in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55195:7"/> the preſence of their Servants they are on the Stage, and 'tis rather action then beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: it may be wert thou a peeper on them in their with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing rooms, thou wouldſt as much wiſh thine eyes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then, as now open. For their vertues, as I will not diſallow the judgement of that reverend Doctor, That 'tis poſſible to finde ſome vertue in ſome women: ſo I cannot believe there is ſuch a grand ſtock of it in any of them, as to command any man out of his ſenſes for the love of it; but I ſuppoſe, as we more wonder to finde a Diamond on the ſhore then
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55195:8"/> on the rock: ſo but a ſpark of vertue in a woman, gets greater reverence then a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died luſtre in the nobler Sex; for 'tis our humour to admire the more where we expect the leſs. The cauſe then of thy love is either from beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or vertue; if from beauty, how wilt thou love her when ſhe is old? If from vertue, why doſt thou covet to lie with her? there needs not that low act of generation to the high communion of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; and I ſhould ſcarce take thee for a platonick Lover, to warm a bed with her. But ſhall I tell thee the cauſe? don't be afraid of truth then;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55195:8"/> thou firſt loveſt her to ſatisfie thy luſt; and if thou after continue to lie with her, 'tis either for want of a better, or 'cauſe thou canſt not be rid of her. For I look on all the perfections in females but as ſo many encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to deſire; and that the beſt of women, like the beſt of ſallads, procure the ſtrongeſt appetite; and in truth 'tis the woman is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, not this, the Sex be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubſtance, and the Miſtris but the ſhadow; or that the rule of thy affection, and this the inſtance. But then thou wilt be goring of me with that common goad
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55195:9"/> of objection, thy ſo much curioſity in choice, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Lady then <hi>Jone.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee tell me, be thy appetite never ſo good, do's thy meat reliſh the worſe for being the cleanlier dreſt? I never knew that good cookery did turn the edge of a good ſtomack; and eſpecially if thou limiteſt thy fancy to one diſh, thou hadſt need to be both long in chooſing, and neat in dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as well to avoid nauſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as to continue provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Remember that July holds not all the year, nor youth all thy life; there is a December and Winter of age that attends on both; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55195:9"/> that paſſion that in its Spring will take fire at any face, will in its Autumn be froſt at all; a bed-ridden palate is ſcarce ſenſible of ſauce, much leſs meat; not the beſt of weapons, how brisk and keen ſoever at the firſt, but after long uſing grows dull, and requires a whetting: ſo that this ſtudious culling of bed-fellows, argues but the ſerious contemplations of mortality, and is no more then a wiſe proviſion for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity. Where <hi>Frank</hi> is your love then? Call'ſt thou that love, that ebs and flows with the blood? that is the brat of a goatiſh humour, meerly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55195:10"/> ſervient to the body, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dead before it? No, the eſſence of that paſſion is as pure and laſting as the ſoul it waits on; a ſacred Veſtall flame, perpetually torrid and unextinguiſhable; 'tis thy under-girdle love thats mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, of flames groſs and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory, which moving in a region lower then thy heart, prove rather flaſhes then ſteady fires. I know thou art no ſtranger to multitude of examples that have beene hotter then <hi>Italians</hi> in the chaſe of their games, and more frozen then <hi>Scythians</hi> after the taking it, that in the ſame year have been ready
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55195:10"/> to die of contraries, both love and hate; and with the ſame eagerneſs ſtudied both a marriage and divorce; that have not more long'd to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, then having obtained, to deſert their hopes, and their loves periſh'd together, the fruition of one the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the other. But may be thou wilt adde to thy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motive, that of wealth, ſhe's rich. Nay now I hear thee, and do ſo far allow thee to court the Lady for her fortune, as I would the Chambermaid for her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris; but have a care of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in earneſt, or letting in of love farther then thy
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55195:11"/> tongue; a ſigh or two in the preſence if thou wilt, but no ejaculations in private; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a difference betwixt acting and ſuffering a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be nothing the ſadder though nothing the richer; like a good Souldier riſe not ſo repulſt from one Leaguer, but to retaine ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough preſently for another, that in a while thy ſoul will become face-proof, the later beauty the pellet of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, till variety give the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to thy judgment, &amp; make thee a Catholick Servant, but no particular Lover. But thou wilt juſtifie yet farther; thou haſt a fortune of thine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55195:11"/> own, and the weightineſs of that requires a partner in the managing it. I don't gainſay it; nay I am ſo much of thy ſide, that I think a wife in no caſe more allowable, then either for the getting or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of an Eſtate. As, for thy love-marrying, I rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it both the paradiſe and purgatory of fools. But yet this <hi>Frank</hi> is onely an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for a wife, not love, and think me no enemy to marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but to the fondneſs of thy deſire; I would have thee get a wife, but not to loſe thy ſelf; to ſerve thy oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, but to maſter thy paſſions; ſo to love with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55195:12"/> as not to woe without ſenſe. Credit me, I do not at all think it to ſavour of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, ſeriouſly to court and marry too, and yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing'd by any ſpark of love, though I cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the temptations of the other Sex; for I rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon them amongſt their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: yet that reaſon, or the ſoul and gallantry of man, ſhould be baſely proſtituted to them, I ſhould as ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve an Eagle to ſtoop at flies, or Divinity at toys. I conceive <hi>Frank,</hi> the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thy marrying ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens not thy judgement to this one Lady; I would have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55195:12"/> thee to look on her as not without companions, and then if thou makeſt an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky caſt of it, thy fortune will have this comfort, thou art no loſer, though no win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Prethee why ſhould not a woman be view'd with as little ardour as an handſome Statue? or what is the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of fleſh, as to the eye, above that of marble? If thou comeſt into a ſpacious Gallery variouſly behung, thou canſt walk it round, look on this Picture and like it, then turn thy face and forget it in the beauty of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; there needing no more to the aſpect of a face,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55195:13"/> then of Imagery, but onely the complacency of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, and the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Authour. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are a kinde of traffique too: If thou comeſt to a ſhop, ſeeſt a commodity and likeſt it, thou cheapen'ſt it; if thou bargaineſt, thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt it, if not, to the next ſtanding, the Markets full and free. I tell thee 'tis an injury no leſs to nature then reaſon, to impale all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction within the circuit of one creature. Now after all this, do I expect thou ſhouldſt bid me turn the Tables and play my ſelfe the queſtion, Was I never in love? Troth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55195:13"/> 
                  <hi>Frank</hi> I cannot excuſe my ſelfe from the vanities of youth, may be I have; but let me remember thee, I have had rattles and hobbi-horſes too in my daies, but I have left them, and now look on them and thy thoughts with the ſame diſdain. That Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner that hath ſcaped a rock, may be a Pilot to the next paſſenger. 'Tis my faith now, that 'tis as poſſible to be ſick of the plague a year, as of love a day; and I doubt not, when time ſhall ripen both thy judgement and age, but thou wilt then ſit a moſt ſtrict judge upon thy ſelf, and think no cenſure too ſevere
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55195:14"/> to thy preſent follies, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity too bountifull to the true advice of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thy true Friend, J. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>PRethee, dear Friend, do not burn <hi>Diana</hi>'s Temple onely to be talked of: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>wits</hi> (like ſpirits of the lower <hi>Region)</hi> once conjured up, muſt be ſet on work, though of miſchief. I muſt confeſs thou ventureſt hard
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55195:14"/> on the <hi>paradoxology</hi> of thy brain, that dareſt enter the Liſts <hi>Athanaſius-like, contra mundum;</hi> diſputing that with thy <hi>pen,</hi> which the World from <hi>Adam,</hi> and thy ſelf by thy practice proveſt <hi>undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> What is ſaid in caſe of <hi>Religion,</hi> a little <hi>Philoſophy</hi> makes men <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough confirms them in the <hi>truth,</hi> is true of thee in point of <hi>love;</hi> of which and its objects thou art no more competent a <hi>Judg,</hi> then a <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coat</hi> is of a Moot-caſe. Did I not know that all <hi>wonder</hi> proceeded of <hi>ignorance,</hi> and that people moſt admire what they leaſt underſtand, I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55195:15"/> ſhould wonder at thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that a man of thy <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>complexion,</hi> and born of a Mother, ſhould call that <hi>ſtumbling,</hi> which is ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and naturall a <hi>motion;</hi> fall out with Love and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yet by thy own <hi>confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> underſtand neither. Thou turneſt <hi>Andabate</hi> and fighteſt blindfold, not knowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom, or for what. I prethee, Friend, what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Girle has ſleighted thy <hi>Madrigals,</hi> and diſentertained thy affections, that thou quarrelleſt and fallſt at defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the whole Sex? He that ſaid all <hi>Crecians</hi> were liers, was himſelf a <hi>Crecian:</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55195:15"/> and thou condemneſt all Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as mad, yet art thy ſelf a Lover, and conſequently <hi>mad,</hi> or elſe more mad that thou art not a Lover. I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet knew any deſpiſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> but thoſe that could not be <hi>Monarchs.</hi> Every man in this is a <hi>Huntſman,</hi> who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſhort of the <hi>Hare,</hi> cries, <hi>Hang her, 'tis dry meat.</hi> Among the reſt of thy wonders, thou maiſt put this for one, that I who am unconcerned, ſhould at this diſtance take up the <hi>cudgels</hi> in defence of a friend, whom thou haſt laught into ſilence; but the proverb excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes me, <hi>He whom ſorrow makes dumb, deſerves double pity.</hi> For
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55195:16"/> my part, I muſt confeſs I love to <hi>ſleep in a whole skin,</hi> and not to engage in anothers quarrell, unleſs he will lend me his <hi>skull</hi> to bear the blows: but this being the common cauſe, 'tis pity <hi>truth</hi> ſhould be out-worded, and her innocence be ſuſpected to want clearneſs, meerly for want of clearing. There is no man more unfit for this work then I, having been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as <hi>atheiſtical</hi> in love as thy ſelf; and ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Opponent</hi> to thy <hi>Theſis,</hi> that I have ever been a noted <hi>Aſſertor</hi> of thy <hi>Doctrine,</hi> till <hi>experience</hi> reformed my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and makes me look on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55195:16"/> my former error with regret and diſdain. 'Tis ſo far from being a wonder to me, that one pleaſant, affable and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable, one that has view'd variety of <hi>beauties,</hi> ſhould fall in love with one <hi>woman,</hi> that I wonder how it could be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe: none being fitter for love then one ſo qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; nor can any finde a <hi>beſt,</hi> that have not view'd all. That <hi>Love per ſe</hi> is the ruine of its ſubject, I deny; yet I allow it may be <hi>accidentally</hi> true, and be a <hi>paſſion</hi> not the leſs noble. And as I would not have it onely reſtrained to <hi>woman</hi> for its object: ſo I would not have them totally
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55195:17"/> excluded. And truly I am ſo far from believing that <hi>Sex</hi> not an object of love, that I can hardly admit of any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. That Love has ſeveral objects, as Heaven, Vertue, and the reſt which you rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up, with many more, I deny not. But all they, as <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> objects, are ſo far from being <hi>adaequate,</hi> that they draw love in ſeverall <hi>denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> as <hi>piety, duty, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> &amp;c. And but that ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs would be thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way on thee, and any thing here but <hi>ſophiſtry</hi> uſeleſs, I could tell thee from the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that <hi>Love</hi> is onely an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion of the ſoul to its object;</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55195:17"/> which is, whatever is <hi>attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive:</hi> and that naturally <hi>man</hi> loves himſelf beſt and firſt, and all other things in <hi>ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> to himſelf; and that whatever is moſt like <hi>man</hi> in nature and habit, is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt <hi>object</hi> of his love. Then 'twill follow (whether you will or no) that no object is ſo proper as <hi>woman.</hi> But thou'lt laugh at theſe old-faſhion'd grounds, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them like <hi>Harry</hi>'s <hi>cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces.</hi> To abſtract <hi>Love</hi> from <hi>ſenſuality</hi> in a naturall ſenſe, is both impoſſible and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it deriving a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence from the ſenſitive ſoul, and being a paſſion from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55195:18"/> which <hi>bruits</hi> are not exempt. Nay that very thing which you call <hi>ſenſuality,</hi> and will allow it to derive its <hi>legitima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> onely from an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, may ſhew an ancienter <hi>coat</hi> then Ordinances; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely way chalked out by <hi>nature</hi> for propagation and preſervation of every ſpecies. So that your <hi>Epithites</hi> and <hi>Synonoma</hi>'s of concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and carnal appetite, &amp;c. I attribute to the luxuriance of your fancy; and muſt tell you, we can eaſily give you and your ways the like <hi>tearms</hi> without the help of a <hi>Sylva.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> your main <hi>beſitancy</hi> is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are you <hi>cauſes</hi> of love?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55195:18"/>
'Tis not bare <hi>red</hi> and <hi>white</hi> that are either cauſes of, or colours for it, but the <hi>ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>contexture</hi> of both. I never loved my Miſtris face, becauſe fair, but becauſe I liked it, and thereby thought it ſo, and I therefore thought it ſo, becauſe <hi>hers:</hi> ſo that ſhould <hi>time</hi> or <hi>accident</hi> (from which no face has a protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) alter the <hi>complexion</hi> in the eye, I'd retain the ſame <hi>Idea</hi> ſtill in mine. Next, for the Gentlemans <hi>change</hi> (with which you upbraid him) much may be pleaded in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: for beſides the great delight in <hi>variety,</hi> I know no reaſon why, if a man finde
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55195:19"/> himſelf in an <hi>errour,</hi> he may not repent and take a new courſe. Nor may you call it <hi>prodigality</hi> of affection; he that grounds his love right, is above uncertainties, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the true cauſe of love, which is <hi>ſympathy,</hi> cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh before its object. And becauſe you ſay, <hi>Beauty is a Chymaera, and every man a pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that carves to himſelf a Miſtris;</hi> will you from thence infer; that becauſe all men do not think one face <hi>beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> no man ſhould think any ſo? And I appeal to the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> of <hi>Divines,</hi> whether for a Lover to chooſe his own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, and love her, or court
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55195:19"/> her, be a piece of <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>paganiſm.</hi> Nor can you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that <hi>manners, carriage</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> are incentives to love; and that theſe things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally viſible in that Sex by any that look not through <hi>ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of <hi>prejudice.</hi> But he that has an ill ſight diſlikes all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Thou haſt an <hi>humour</hi> in thine eyes, whereby thou canſt not diſcern <hi>action</hi> from <hi>behaviour;</hi> I like it not the worſe if acquired; no more then I do a good <hi>Scholar</hi> that ſpeaks <hi>Latine</hi> by the <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</hi> That there are <hi>arcana imperii</hi> among them, as well as us, is undeniable; for if all were as they appear, they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55195:20"/> would be rather <hi>Angels</hi> then <hi>women.</hi> 'Tis true, much <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>deceptio viſus</hi> is in both Sexes in point of Courtſhip, whereby they <hi>reciprocally</hi> draw their expectations to a height <hi>unobtainable,</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>enjoyments</hi> convince both Sexes of a <hi>handſom</hi> (but commonly an <hi>equall) cheat.</hi> I ſhall not onely allow of that Doctors charity, that held, <hi>That 'tis poſſible ſome vertue may be found in ſome women:</hi> but alſo ſhall experimentally adde, <hi>That much vertue may be found in many.</hi> 'Tis not for nothing that all vertues are <hi>declined</hi> by <hi>Grammarians</hi> with <hi>haec,</hi> and fancied by Painters
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55195:20"/> in <hi>female</hi> ſhadows. Vertues are like Diamonds, rare and ſmall; nor ſhould we eſteem them were they to be bought by the pound. I take <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> to be cauſes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; but I mean not by beauty the meer <hi>ſuperficies</hi> of a viſage, but the <hi>ſymmetry</hi> of parts; and he that grounds his affection rightly on that, findes a becoming <hi>beauty,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in old <hi>age. Vertue</hi> alſo I conceive a cauſe of <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>love</hi> a <hi>motive</hi> of <hi>copulation.</hi> Nor is generation for the communion of vertues, but <hi>propagation</hi> of <hi>iſſue;</hi> ſince 'tis an undoubted <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nature,</hi> that all creatures deſire and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55195:21"/> endeavour <hi>perpetuation.</hi> You call <hi>luſt</hi> the cauſe of <hi>love;</hi> 'tis true, if you take all <hi>altitudes</hi> by your own <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſtaff, 'tis ſo to you: ſo the <hi>Wolf</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives all creatures to eat <hi>raw fleſh,</hi> becauſe he do's. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine ſuch a <hi>ſtoical a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy</hi> in men, unleſs in <hi>Euto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> but that we do and may make that which you call <hi>luſt,</hi> a part of <hi>love.</hi> Nor is that paſſion it ſelf blameable, but <hi>circumſtances</hi> may make it ſo: for the <hi>Stoicks</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves got children, and did not deny the being of deſires in men, but their domineer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over Reaſon. Nor is it the work of a <hi>wiſe</hi> man to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55195:21"/> without <hi>paſſions,</hi> but above them. Conſider man as with a ſoul compounded of Will and Reaſon, the conqueſt of the <hi>will</hi> in this life, can be but by <hi>ſynechdoche;</hi> which being conſidered, it will follow, That men abſtracted from deſires of this nature, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be <hi>looked</hi> for, then <hi>found.</hi> And for your <hi>erratical love,</hi> that is ſo planitary and unfixed, it ſhews its own weakneſſe, but not your ſtrength; though it be peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patetical, it makes not you a Philoſopher; ſince <hi>Love,</hi> like <hi>Sun-beams,</hi> being diffuſed, are but faint: but contracted to one Object, are fervent and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55195:22"/> calefactory. <hi>Wives</hi> are not <hi>Quelque chores,</hi> in whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>variety</hi> breeds delight, but are ſolid food which never nauſeate ſound ſtomachs. For a man to love Vertue abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from its ſubject, is to fancy a <hi>Chymaera;</hi> but Vertue in a woman is an undoubted <hi>motive.</hi> As to your ſimilitude of <hi>Joane and my Lady;</hi> take the whole Proverb; put in <hi>(in the dark)</hi> and you'r an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, 'Tis not want of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, but due diſcerning; nor <hi>is</hi> ſhe as good, but <hi>ſeems</hi> ſo. The Cuckow once ſang better then the Nightingale; but remember who was Judge. Times ſwift motion,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55195:22"/> and youths tranſitorineſs are <hi>common places</hi> in the beaten roads, where ever travelling <hi>wit</hi> baits and refreſhes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his <hi>pilgrimage.</hi> But yet <hi>Deſires</hi> being part of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> and ſo immortall, do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in age, but onely alter their motives and object. Nor is the world barren of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of aged men, eagerly deſiring and performing rites of conjuncture with women. As for thoſe <hi>changeable</hi> and <hi>quick-ſilver</hi> minds which <hi>love</hi> and <hi>loath</hi> in a moment, 'tis their vice, and may give you this notion, <hi>That as their love can ſo ſoon and eaſily change into diſdain:</hi> ſo your preſent
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55195:23"/> ſcorn may turn to a dotage on the like ground. And though perhaps you have not yet been in love, 'tis <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne malum</hi> (ſince you will call it ſo) like the ſmall pox, <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one hath been, or muſt be troubled with it;</hi> and bodies unacquainted with leſſer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, are irrecoverably ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of greater. Your wary advice to your friend, <hi>to love with diſcretion,</hi> I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and commend; and for my part were I to love again, would not go a foot further then my <hi>counterpart</hi> ſhould meet me; but where I found reall love, I would ſcorne to be out-vied, being of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55195:23"/> his reſolution, <hi>No crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould conquer me with love or hatred.</hi> T'is not good to, play the Butcher with that naked Sex that have no arms but to imbrace with, nor Emprick-like, kill them by whole-ſale. I never yet met any of either Sex good at the ſport, but at laſt they met with a requitall. 'Tis within the memory of man ſince a pregnant Spark furniſhed with two of your Cardinall Vertues, <hi>wit</hi> and <hi>diſdain,</hi> ſlung his <hi>fire-balls</hi> of <hi>contempt</hi> on the whole Sex, courted ſome into <hi>dotage,</hi> and then <hi>jeered</hi> 'um; who at laſt fell foul on a Kitchin-wench, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55195:24"/> doated, who repayed him with the ſame devices; and which was worſt, at laſt in deſpight married him. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micida</hi> is of both Genders, and belongs to both Sexes. Your other points of marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for wealth and yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, I ſhall agree to with ſilence. But I would not make wealth my Miſtris's Maſter, while <hi>woman</hi> ſtands by like the <hi>Chamber-maid</hi> with a <hi>broom</hi> to attend her. Let my Miſtris be a <hi>figure,</hi> and her portion the <hi>Cyphers;</hi> which added to her, advance her much, but of themſelves ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing. <hi>Paſſionate Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> ſhould, but cannot, be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55195:24"/> avoided by all; every one is not <hi>Hercules:</hi> but diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may and muſt be ſhun'd by all. There is no Souldier, beleaguers a Gariſon, but with hopes to come off <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched:</hi> no Lover attempts a Miſtris, but hopes for frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without <hi>bloudſhed;</hi> yet the Souldier may receive a <hi>ſhot,</hi> and the Woer a <hi>repulſe;</hi> and that which he intends for a ſin, oft proves a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He that lives a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Woer, may at laſt come to the <hi>purgatory</hi> of a generall contempt. But methinks (Friend) you wheel about and approve that which at firſt you decried; there might
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55195:25"/> be ſome hopes of agreement and <hi>hand-ſhaking</hi> between us. Allow <hi>love</hi> and <hi>marriage</hi> and I will joyn with thee againſt dotage; and would have Love ſequeſtred from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as much as thy minde from this <hi>obſtinacy.</hi> But I ſee the Devil has alwais a cloven foot; you would now allow of <hi>marriage</hi> without <hi>love,</hi> and confound love and dotage, as if the ſame. To wed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out love, is to be tied by the loyns like a <hi>Monkey</hi> to a <hi>bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt;</hi> neither is it poſſible to court or marry without love, as you write, for that want of love turns courtſhip to <hi>flattery,</hi> and marriage to a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55195:25"/> 
                  <hi>bargain.</hi> That Women are Natures <hi>Errata,</hi> with <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> I acknowledge; and that they ſtudy temptations, is undoubtedly true: but yet that they do it not alone, your own example proves; who by this fancy of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>womaniſm</hi> tempt the Sex ſo much, that I could wiſh my ſelf one to dote on thee. Do not call the lawfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>intermixture</hi> of both Sexes to be a baſe proſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Reaſon, Soul, and Gallantry of a man; 'tis ſo falſe and groundleſs, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves no anſwer but the <hi>lye.</hi> Let thy friend alone with his choice, and if he think her
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55195:26"/> ſo, ſhe is <hi>pieceleſs;</hi> only I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your Caution, <hi>While he ſeeks to win her, let him not loſe himſelf; nor ſhoot away all his ſhot at one volley, but keep a reſerve for a freſh encounter;</hi> 'tis but diſcretion. And now to anſwer your ſimilitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Queſtion, Why a woman cannot be viewed with as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ardour as a Statue? it is <hi>becauſe a Statue is not a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor directly like a Woman;</hi> if it could be, <hi>Pigmation</hi> will tell you there may be like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, nor is the influence different as to the eye, but the power that actuates it; if a man view a thouſand Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, he generally likes one
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55195:26"/> beſt, and having peruſed all, returns to that; and though the Market be free, and Wares various, a good Chapman ſticks to what he beſt fancies, and deals in it. Neither is all perfection thereby impaled in one Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but there may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſuppoſed in one, to content one. <hi>That your ſelf hath ever loved,</hi> I queſtion; but that you have <hi>fancied,</hi> and <hi>miſt,</hi> may be true; but you cannot thereby go out a cometetent <hi>Tutor.</hi> Nor ſhould I ever take that <hi>Mariner</hi> for my Pilot, who hath no other experience then <hi>ſplitting his own Ship;</hi> firſt guide your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55195:27"/> own <hi>Veſſell</hi> to the <hi>Port,</hi> before you take another to your management and ſteerage. What it is to be ſick of Love or the Plague, you know much alike, and ſo ſhall be believed, having ſtudied both but in ſhape; for my part, I have knowne many ſick of Love, and yet recovered; but the Plague I have no skill in. My deſire is, that you partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of your own <hi>counſell;</hi> ſuſpend your ſevere cenſure to your friend, and ſit firſt a ſtrict Judge on your ſelf, till <hi>time</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> ripen your judgement and change your minde. Which I hope I ſhall not longer expect,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55195:27"/> then untill you have ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peruſed and weighed the experimentall directions and wholſome advice of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Thine, and thy Friends Friend. A. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:55195:28"/>
            <head>A Letter to a Friend, delivering an Opinion concerning the <hi>Scotch</hi> Riſing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat you may receive an account of the <hi>Scotch</hi> buſineſs, and that there hath been ſuch irreſolute altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about the <hi>Treaties</hi> lately, 'tis fit you know this <hi>Northern</hi> ſtorm, like a new Diſeaſe, hath ſo far poſed the <hi>Doctors</hi> of State, that as yet they have not given it a name; though perchance they all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55195:28"/> firmly believe it to be <hi>rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion;</hi> and therefore, Sir, it is no wonder if theſe do here as the learned in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> who when they know not certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the grief, preſcribe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines ſometimes too ſtrong, ſometimes too weak. The truth is, we here iudge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Scotch</hi> Affaires much after the rate as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals</hi> do of the <hi>Moon;</hi> the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple think it no bigger then a buſhell, and ſome likewiſe think it a vaſt World, with ſtrange things undiſcovered in it; two ill waies of caſting it up; ſure the firſt will make us too <hi>ſecure;</hi> the other too <hi>fearfull.</hi> I confeſs I know not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55195:29"/> how to write in the <hi>middle,</hi> and ſet it right; nor do I think you know; ſince I ſhould believe the queſtion rather to be, A <hi>King</hi> or no <hi>King?</hi> then A <hi>Biſhop</hi> or no <hi>Biſhop?</hi> In great mutinies and inſurrections of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, pretences ſpeciouſly conſcionable were never wanting; and indeed they are neceſſary; for <hi>rebellion</hi> is of it ſelf ſo ugly, that did it not put on the vizard of <hi>Religion,</hi> it would <hi>affright</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>draw</hi> people unto it; and being <hi>drawn,</hi> could not <hi>hold</hi> them without it. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary cords</hi> that ſeem to faſten man to Heaven, have
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55195:29"/> tied things here below faſter then any other obligation. If it be <hi>liberty of conſcience</hi> they ask; it is a fooliſh requeſt, ſeeing they have it already, and muſt have in deſpight of power. For as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Jews, Nemo cogitur cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere invitus.</hi> If they exerciſe that <hi>liberty,</hi> 'tis dangerous; for not three men are of the ſame <hi>opinion</hi> in all; and then each Family muſt have a War within it ſelf. Look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the long Preparations, and conſider withall that <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are ceaſed,</hi> and therefore they could not foretell this <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook</hi> ſhould be ſent to them, and you will conclude they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55195:30"/> rather imploy'd <hi>conſcience</hi> then <hi>conſcience</hi> them. Inquiry after the <hi>Leaders,</hi> and you will hardly finde them <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> or men of ſo high ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctity, that they ſhould order <hi>Religion; Leſley</hi> himſelf if his ſore were ſearched, would certainly be found one, who becauſe he could not live well there, took up a trade of <hi>killing men</hi> abroad; and now is return'd to kill men at home. If you will have my opinion, I think their quarrell to the <hi>King</hi> is the ſame they have to the <hi>Sun</hi> that he doth not warm them ſo much, nor viſit them ſo oft as he doth others. <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:55195:30"/> and <hi>Nature</hi> placed them in the ſhade, and they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with the <hi>King</hi> for it: To conclude, this is the <hi>caſe;</hi> the great and wiſe Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath placed theſe <hi>Beaſts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out-fields, and they would needs break <hi>hedges</hi> to come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the <hi>Garden.</hi> This is the belief of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:55195:31"/>
            <head>A Whore</head>
            <p>IS one of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, that carries fire in the tail, to deſtroy the ſtanding corn, She goes under the name of a decayed Gentlewoman; and indeed ſhe is gentle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, a half Crown will make her come to hand. The Devil and ſhe are co-partners in undoing, for one ſpoiles the body, the other the ſoul. Turn-up ſhe affects above all roots in the Garden. She cares not for the <hi>Bridewell,</hi> having lain often at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55195:31"/> Ward. Her walk is <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden;</hi> and her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change a Tavern. He that goes to ſalute her, is decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for ſhe is very coy of her lips, and therefore bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks them about with paint. Her breath ſtinkes worſe then a Bear-garden; her furniture conſiſts of a Playſter-box, a Periwig, and a Looking-glaſs; beſides a Pimp, which ſhe accounts one of her neceſſary imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. She is a ſhe-Bias, and can ſay, <hi>Omnia mea mecum porto.</hi> She is a preſervative againſt a hard froſt; and a Regiment of them will beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> for they carry
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55195:32"/> fire about them. Her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if any, are like wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls, and found in the Kings high-way. She is not ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, but delights in fallings; yet by her falling her Stalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons riſe. She is a hackney Jade, and lets every foole ride her; a Barbers chaire, as ſoon as one is out, another is in. She is a very Butcher, and ſells her fleſh by the ſtone; one may buy her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whole at the price of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. She is like a Medlar, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ripe till rotten; like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, ſhe thrives the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the more ſhe is trod. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty ſhe is in her Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith, and then from thence
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55195:32"/> ſhe declines; for the pox, or rotten teeth, &amp;c. will write her ſtale, or ugly, and trading will decay; and then her on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preferment is the degree of a Bawd, where three Strong-water bottles, an ounce of Tobacco, and two Countrey Wenches, ſets her up; and ſhe drives a trade till <hi>Shrove-tueſday;</hi> and a Cart and a bunch of Turnips is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of her labours; and the <hi>Bridewell</hi> the limbo of both body and bones.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:55195:33"/>
            <head>A Patentee</head>
            <p>WAs ſometimes a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of Fortunes, but being caſt over-board by his own riot or folly, layes hold of the next thing he meets with. He is begot like a Mule, between a Courtier and a Citizen, but turns Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide to both. No aire nips him ſo much as a Weſt winde coming from the Parliament-Houſe, for that brings him to the Falling-ſickneſs; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique and his re-private never are in conjunction; but
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55195:33"/> like <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> when one ſets the other riſeth. He is an excellent Alchymiſt, and can draw Gold out of Sope, Candles, and Marrow-bones, and what not? Nothing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers him ſo much as the ſound of a Reformation; for then he is projecting to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Patent to hang him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Like a Louce, he ſhrowds on the ſhoulders of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for that is his main protection. All honeſt men ſhun his company, and he theirs; in which regard you may call him a Separatiſt. His walk is <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> or the <hi>Court,</hi> with his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Papers, becauſe he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55195:34"/> would be taken for a man of note. The Monopoliſt and he, like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> twins, both live and die together. In his chamber his Glaſs and he are in a deep conſultation, how to ſet his face that it may go even with the times; like a Watch, whereof his tongue is the Alarum. His pretences are faire, for the benefit and eaſe of the Subject; To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſome grievance (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own poverty;) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Trade, (meaning of Patentees) and to prevent diſorders; to which he rather adds a ſaile then a ballaſt. He has little skill in the Law, but onely in the penall Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55195:34"/> and that in a defenſive way to play the knave in a circle, and yet keep out of their bounds to prevent hanging: and leſs in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, unleſs to fiſh by <hi>Peter</hi>'s example, for ſuch fiſh as have Money in their mouths. His Religion is commonly but skin-deep, it may appear in his countenance, but it never comes near his heart; 'tis writ upon changeable Taffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, for good and lawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; his Religion and his Practice make him like the new invented Pictures, one way an Angel, another way a Devil. All his life is a continued <hi>Cataline</hi>'s Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55195:35"/> he and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth are like two feet, if one riſe, the other falls; if both chance to riſe together, 'tis but a leap, that the fall may be the greater. He feeds upon new Projects; his drink is the tears of the poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers; and commonly his Livery is the ruine of ſome Corporation. His diſeaſe lies in his ears, for he is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infected with a Pillory; which at laſt comes into his neck, and <hi>Tiburne</hi> ends him; where his onely glory is, that he died for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths good.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55195:35"/>
            <head>A Politick</head>
            <p>IS one that makes Heaven bow to Earth; he placeth his <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> in Earths felicity, and depends on no other Providence but the reach of his own brain. His Religion is but the vizard of his policy; and whatever vertue he has, craft is the keeper of it. His looks are candid, and hypocriſie is the onely Saint he adores. All his diſcourſes are obſcure and ambiguous; like the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in the <hi>Delphick</hi> Oracle;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55195:36"/> you may underſtand the words, but not the meaning. He is like an Aſpen-tree, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very winde of Greatneſſe blowes him, and he bends. Is his Prince valourous? he is daring; covetous? he is ſparing; laſcivious? he is wanton; religious? he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends much; his heart is a Theatre, wherein all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are preſented, and his face pantomimicall. He is of that mans Religion, with whom he talks; a <hi>Caeſarean,</hi> a <hi>Pompeian,</hi> which ſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails; he'l cry, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p with them,</hi> and, <hi>Down with them,</hi> all in a breath. Like a Water-man, he looks one way and rowes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55195:36"/> another; or like a Lapwing, keeps moſt noiſe when ſhe is fartheſt from her neſt; or a cunning Fencer, that ſeldom makes a blow without a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie; ſuller of Queſtions then Anſwers; rather deſiring to know anothers ſecrets, then bewray his own. Pleaſures he is not much delighted in, but onely like the Dog at <hi>Nilus,</hi> laps as he runs, for fear of the Crocodile. Every one that he deals with, he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hath the Maſter-reach in cunning; and therefore ſtill carries both eyes open. His ſight is ſtrong enough to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend dangers in <hi>Embrio,</hi> and ſo quells them before
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55195:37"/> ſhape or form make them ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible. If a Contract blow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably, he hoiſeth ſailes, and with it ſteers his Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; if a croſs gale comes to his main under-ground De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, he thruſts out the Oars of fair Pretences through the Port-holes of his conſeience. He would be accounted eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans friend, that he might know his ſecrets. All his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are tipped with fair Pretences, yet are directed to himſelf; and therefore looks no higher. Whatever his Theam be, his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is his own ends: yet he is often contented to do any cheap courteſies; and makes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55195:37"/> himſelf very joyfull and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in an opportunity, ſo as he be ſure to be no loſer by it. His cap and knee, his ſmiles and good words, are all at a minutes warning, to be dealt about on all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In a word, he is one that loves no man, but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; nor will truſt any; nor indeed any wiſe man him, farther then he ſees him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:55195:38"/>
            <head>A Clubber</head>
            <p>IS a Hogs-head ſet on two ſtumps, fit for no uſe but to hold Liquor; the Tavern only is his <hi>ubi</hi> and the proper place of his reſidence; any other where he is like a Fiſh out of the water, who doth nothing but gape. He thinks Nature gave him a mouth, not to ſpeak, but to drink off his Liquor, for that is the main uſe he puts it to; he drinks not to live (as Nature commands) but lives to drink. Of all the Miracles
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55195:38"/> that ever Chriſt did, he thinks none ſo meritorious for the ſalvation of his ſoul, as the turning water into Wine; and he in imitation can work a miracle too; for he can turn a whole Shop of Wares into a Pint-pot. His onely enquiry is, where dwells the beſt Sack or Claret? You ſhall finde him and his Tribe about the declining part of the day, at rendezvous, like a Conſtellation fixt in the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer Region of a known Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern; where their noſes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like Comets, and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend drough; there they are accommodated with a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Room, a half-Pint, ſome
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55195:39"/> clean Pipes, and a Jordan. Their firſt Diſcourſe is a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Vote about the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Wine; the next paire of half-Pints produces News; where each puffs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the inſide of a Diurnal; but for want of that, the main Scene is, who were drunk the night before, and how they reel'd home. They are internally <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and very exact in making clean the inſide of the Glaſs; their ſtricteſt Criticiſme is, <hi>Drink off your Cup.</hi> At laſt, when it ſtrikes twelve, they make a liquor'd Reckoning, drink their Wives Health, in whoſe defence they are dutifully
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55195:39"/> drunk, till they loſe their owne; and then they ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger home to bed, and finde it in ſmall beer in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <head>A politick Citizen</head>
            <p>IS a lump of <hi>combuſtible ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> whom the leaſt ſpark of newes fires into a <hi>blaze</hi> of unlikely conjectures; he meaſures all the deſigns of Foraign News by the line of <hi>Stow's Chronicle;</hi> which he never hears read, but out flies a piece of <hi>nonſenſe,</hi> which he miſcalls State-policy, able to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55195:40"/> confound <hi>Machiavel.</hi> He much haunts the <hi>Poſthouſe</hi> to note into what forms men concoct their faces at the reading of Letters; he frequents the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> in the <hi>Poſtmeridian</hi> hours, becauſe then men em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty themſelves of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; his only factorage is <hi>news;</hi> viewing a Bill of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> he ſwears 'tis a <hi>Libell.</hi> Tell him of a <hi>Curranto</hi> and he's in Heaven; he takes an <hi>Almanack</hi> of foul weather for one of <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Propheſies. Upon hearing of a Victory, or loſs of a <hi>Sconce,</hi> he is enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and blames the State that he was not a <hi>Generall;</hi> he extolls the <hi>Low-Countreys</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:55195:40"/> Government above any <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> becauſe the fat <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> rule the roaſt; he holds it impoſſible for the State e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be ruined, becauſe it ſwims in <hi>Butter.</hi> His face is a piece of <hi>Stenography,</hi> where all <hi>Bicheliews</hi> deſigns are writ in <hi>ſhort-hand.</hi> He keeps a common <hi>place-book</hi> of hard State-words, which though nor he nor his <hi>Engliſh Dictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> underſtand, he after an <hi>Aldermans</hi> Plumb-broth Feaſt <hi>ſpews</hi> out among the learned Fraternity; and is therefore ſlander'd with the name of a <hi>Politician,</hi> and he turns <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> and believes it; for they had rather ignorantly admire
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55195:41"/> his ſpeeches, then go to the price of <hi>underſtanding</hi> them. All the paſſages he hears are <hi>Stratagems;</hi> if he hear but a Ballad, he ſmells <hi>Treaſon</hi> in it; he cannot endure <hi>Plays,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are <hi>Plots</hi> in them; ask him a queſtion, you <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine</hi> him; anſwer him with ſilence, he takes you for a <hi>State Informer;</hi> he tells news by <hi>tale,</hi> not by <hi>weight.</hi> There is no way to ſtrike him dumb but drawing out your <hi>Table-Book;</hi> every man is a <hi>fool</hi> that is not of his <hi>opinion,</hi> but he takes him for an undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wiſe man that applauds his <hi>conjectures;</hi> he ſeldome approves any thing that he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55195:41"/> underſtands, and yet he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves moſt things; he medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates on an old <hi>Manuſcript</hi> more then the <hi>Pentateuch;</hi> he wonders why the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> is put in the end of the Bible, and thinks it a diſgrace; he takes <hi>Brightman</hi> for a better Interpreter then <hi>Daniel;</hi> he cuts the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> out of his Bible, for fear of infection; yet cannot tell why he hates it, but becauſe 'tis <hi>Apocrypho;</hi> and thinks <hi>Solomon</hi> but a fool in ſuffering his wiſdom to be put there. <hi>Monarchy</hi> he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide, but ſays 'tis againſt <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> but thinks <hi>Anarchy</hi> is as old as the <hi>Chaos.</hi> He takes <hi>Malchus</hi>'s Servant
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55195:42"/> to be a Saint, becauſe he had his ear cut; yet thinks him not right of his opinion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had one left. He takes <hi>Peter</hi> for a Popiſh <hi>Biſhop,</hi> becauſe he cut off that eare. Where'ere the Scripture ſays <hi>ſtrive,</hi> he takes it for <hi>fighting;</hi> that makes him ſo in love with <hi>Civill War.</hi> Among his Superiours he is <hi>dumb;</hi> to his inferiours <hi>deaf;</hi> the one he offends by <hi>ſilence,</hi> the other by <hi>prating;</hi> to both he is <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous.</hi> In a word, he is the State <hi>Incendiary,</hi> the Cities <hi>bane,</hi> and Kings <hi>evil.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:55195:42"/>
            <head>A. Schiſmatick.</head>
            <p>IS one of thoſe raſh Servants that will not let the <hi>Wheat</hi> and the <hi>Tares</hi> grow together; but crops off his <hi>haire,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weeds it up, leſt it ſhould hinder the growth of his <hi>ears,</hi> that when the harveſt of <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> comes, they may be reaped by handfulls <hi>for good Conſiderations.</hi> He thinks it impoſſible to be ſaved if ones haire tranſcends his teeth in longitude. He is in the head an <hi>Hermaphridite,</hi> between a Frier and a <hi>Turk,</hi> the one
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55195:43"/> ſhaves round the <hi>head,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>crown,</hi> he both; he hopes to be pulled up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the <hi>ears,</hi> like a <hi>pitcher.</hi> He is a Papiſt turn'd the wrong ſide outwards, and ſo ſtrongly denies their <hi>tenets,</hi> that he grants their <hi>maximies;</hi> his <hi>Religion</hi> and theirs run round in a circle till they meet. He is fallen out with <hi>Learning</hi> ſo, that he thinks <hi>ignorance</hi> his main <hi>ſaving grace;</hi> and would be content to ſpeak no Language but ſanctified <hi>Bulls,</hi> but that the Pope uſeth them; he ſtands much for <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> yet will tie all men from the uſe of <hi>ceremonies; free-will</hi> he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:55195:43"/> cries down in a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> yet maintains that a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> may do what he pleaſe. All his diſcourſe is the <hi>ſand</hi> of <hi>zeal</hi> bound together without the <hi>lime</hi> of <hi>reaſon;</hi> for he calls that <hi>humane Traditions,</hi> and proteſts the Brethren do not uſe it. You cannot vex him more, then to tell him his ſoul is <hi>Gods Image;</hi> for he hates <hi>idolatry.</hi> To ſpeak <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages</hi> (he ſaith) is to glory in the <hi>confuſion</hi> of <hi>Babel;</hi> and to talk <hi>ſenſe,</hi> is to advance <hi>carnall reaſon</hi> above the Spirit. He wears his ſoul, as a <hi>Gallant</hi> that has put on his <hi>Periwig</hi> the back part foremoſt; for whereas his <hi>will</hi> ſhould be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55195:44"/> 
               <hi>judicious,</hi> his <hi>judgement</hi> is <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> He flies <hi>humane Learning</hi> as from a <hi>Serpent;</hi> three words of <hi>Latine</hi> will give him nine <hi>ſtools.</hi> His knowledge, how ſmall ſoever, never ſinks into his heart, but only ſwims in his <hi>brain;</hi> ſtanding bare at a <hi>Sermon</hi> makes his <hi>zeal</hi> catch cold, and that brings <hi>ſnuffling</hi> in the noſe. He is one of the <hi>Attorneys</hi> of <hi>Dovers</hi> Court; and can with more patience <hi>talk</hi> five hours, then <hi>hear</hi> one. In company he is excellent <hi>Phyſick;</hi> for he will either purge your <hi>gall</hi> with <hi>anger,</hi> or your <hi>ſpleen</hi> with <hi>laughter.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt every <hi>new meeting,</hi> he takes in ſtore of <hi>new Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:55195:44"/> to maintain ſome <hi>new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangled</hi> opinion; which when he vents, his <hi>proſelytes</hi> are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd with <hi>admiration,</hi> and thinke him <hi>inſpired</hi> with ſtrange revelations, that he can ſpeake <hi>Engliſh</hi> and they not <hi>under ſtand</hi> him. He will <hi>croſs</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> High-way ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then view a <hi>Croſs</hi> there. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was never ſo corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>Dutch</hi> Comments, as the Scripture is with his; his brain is like the <hi>puddle</hi> at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> into which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Well diſchannels it ſelf, and becomes ſtinking water. When he takes a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his mouth, 'tis in that ſenſe as a <hi>Wolf</hi> takes a <hi>Lamb;</hi> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55195:45"/> but <hi>ſimpliciter.</hi> Tell him of a <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> and he holds his ears, and ſays there is a <hi>myſtery</hi> in that Poſture. Set but his <hi>zeal</hi> on fire, and it will flame, though it ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Kingdome; the only way to confute him is <hi>ſilence</hi> or <hi>laughter.</hi> He is all for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant</hi> Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet wiſhes all the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> Clergie hang'd. He holds a <hi>Stable</hi> as holy as a <hi>Church;</hi> but holds a <hi>Chamber</hi> holier then both, if it be well furniſhed; that is, with a <hi>Bed</hi> and a <hi>Siſter;</hi> and then he cares not how long he <hi>ſtands.</hi> He that would draw the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his <hi>Religion,</hi> had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55195:45"/> need have a Map of all the <hi>Earth,</hi> and of <hi>Hell</hi> too, where his Principles are deeply roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. He will not believe that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ever deſcended into <hi>Hell,</hi> but intends to take a Journey thither himſelf to diſpute with the <hi>Devil.</hi> There let him go for me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:55195:46"/>
            <head>A Gallant</head>
            <p>IS one that Nature made while the World was in a <hi>Chaos,</hi> and therefore deteſts order <hi>ab origine.</hi> He dares uſe his <hi>tongue</hi> againſt Heaven; but ſcarce his hands againſt a <hi>Butterfly.</hi> Is he ſober? his care is how to be <hi>drunk,</hi> is he <hi>drunk?</hi> his next task is how to ſhift the <hi>reckoning.</hi> All his Diſcourſes are butter'd with <hi>Oaths,</hi> which he uſes <hi>Eupho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae gratiâ.</hi> He has worn out all his friends, but the Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and all his <hi>Apparell,</hi> but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55195:46"/> his <hi>Sword;</hi> which he hacks ſometimes againſt a <hi>Mantle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt,</hi> and ſwears he has been in a deſperate encounter; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from a <hi>Bawdy-houſe,</hi> he ſwears he has been in hot ſervice, though his courage be ſoon taken down. Two <hi>French</hi> poſtures he has natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>viz.</hi> to have his <hi>Flanks</hi> and his <hi>haire</hi> fall off; which laſt defect he ſupplies with the mercenary <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> a <hi>Periwig.</hi> His face ſpeaks him no true Subject, becauſe of its frequent <hi>riſings;</hi> to which Rebels his <hi>noſe</hi> is <hi>Standard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer,</hi> and carries the <hi>colours.</hi> His common Notion or <hi>Title<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page</hi> is a <hi>Low-countrey Souldier;</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:55195:47"/> under which vizard he boaſts of Victories and Adventures which he heard diſcourſed of at the laſt Tavern. He ſets his <hi>faith</hi> to ſale, and cries, Who will give moſt? His <hi>Loyalty</hi> laſts no longer then his <hi>Money.</hi> His threats are like <hi>Thunder-claps,</hi> or the motions of <hi>Mountains;</hi> and if a blow be brought forth, 'tis like a <hi>Mouſe;</hi> in the midſt of his fury, if you care not for his menaces, nor fear his blows, he will ſhake hands with you. 'Twere fearfull if his <hi>valour</hi> were as great as his <hi>wickedneſs;</hi> or if his <hi>power</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choed his <hi>will.</hi> Though he be an <hi>Infidell</hi> himſelf, he
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55195:47"/> would have others <hi>believe</hi> his Oaths when he promiſeth payment. You cannot do him a greater diſcourteſie, then to make his <hi>Chyrurgeon</hi> drunk, for then he bewrays his <hi>ſecrets.</hi> He keeps good quarter with his <hi>Landreſs,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould diſcover the ſpots of his <hi>converſation.</hi> The firſt thing he does in morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is to bid a <hi>Pox</hi> take thoſe <hi>Fleas</hi> that bit him at night; which is ſure to be granted; and the laſt thing he doth at night, is to curſe the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> that <hi>cudgell'd</hi> him that day. In the morning, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sun immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his riſe, he paſſes into an
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:55195:48"/> 
               <hi>Ale-houſe;</hi> or if he can get one to ſpend for him, to a <hi>Tavern;</hi> ſo paſſes from <hi>ſigne</hi> to <hi>ſigne,</hi> through a whole <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack</hi> in a day, till he comes to <hi>Aquarius;</hi> and then goes by <hi>water</hi> to a <hi>Bawdy-houſe,</hi> and comes out by <hi>fire.</hi> He believes there is no Signe of <hi>Virgo</hi> left in the World. In the end you ſhall finde him kick'd by his Companions for having no Money about him, which he ſwears is in his other <hi>pockets,</hi> when as he has but only one Suit; and that is threadbare before the Taylor is paid. Thus when he has gone his <hi>round,</hi> and been <hi>abuſed</hi> by his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:55195:48"/> for abuſing them, he reels into the mouths of the <hi>Watch,</hi> and from thence is rowled into the <hi>Counter;</hi> where to his credit, many great Actions are imputed to him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:55195:49"/>
            <head>A Ballad-maker</head>
            <p>IS a Volume of <hi>Rime</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the hand of <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe;</hi> or a <hi>muſicall</hi> Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not yet <hi>tun'd.</hi> An <hi>Ale-houſe</hi> he accounts the only <hi>Helicon;</hi> and the <hi>Ale-drapers</hi> Wife one of the nine <hi>Muſes.</hi> His <hi>wit</hi> runs thick or clear, like the <hi>Ale-barrell.</hi> He is a ſecond <hi>Charon;</hi> for none are wafted over by the way of <hi>Tiburn,</hi> but he receives money for their paſſage. He exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly longs for blazing <hi>Stars,</hi> Earthquakes, Dearths, or
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:55195:49"/> ſtrange accidents. The <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> keep conſtant correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency with him, that he may compoſe their <hi>Libels</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Metre;</hi> and being whipt or Pillory'd for it, he rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, ſaying that he ſuffers for the <hi>truth.</hi> His Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons call him <hi>Poet</hi> at every word, but 'tis in a jeer; and being patient to bear all ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, believes it, and bears it. Call him <hi>Gooſe</hi> or <hi>Wood-cock,</hi> he is enraged; but yet had rather eat your words, then you ſhould. He is ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of no Argument but <hi>beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and that alone drives him out of your company. He is in pay by the Countrey
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:55195:50"/> Wenches, to write <hi>Love Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to lamentable <hi>Tunes,</hi> which they ſing to the <hi>Cows,</hi> and make them weep <hi>milky</hi> tears to hear them. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Vaticans where his Books are preſerved, are the windows and walls of an <hi>Ale-houſe</hi> in the Countrey. He like the Emblematiſts, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to an Engraver; but only his Wood carver hath certain common Places; a <hi>man</hi> and a <hi>woman</hi> ſerve like <hi>Panpharmacons,</hi> for all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He is a dutifull Son of the <hi>Church,</hi> and loves no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in <hi>Muſicks;</hi> but they go like <hi>Hopkins</hi> and <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> to the Tune of the ſame.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:55195:50"/> He is in no better <hi>cue</hi> to write a lamentable Story, then when he is <hi>Mawdlen-drunk;</hi> his brain is the common-ſhore of <hi>Poetry;</hi> the ſtreams which he ſucks from <hi>Poets,</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files with the muddy ſtinking puddles of his Additions. There is many a man is made a <hi>Martyr</hi> by his Elegies; wherein his <hi>Encomiaſticks</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the very aſhes, and <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically</hi> tear the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Hercules</hi> with a ſmiling countenance. In a word; he is the <hi>Suburbs</hi> of a <hi>Poet;</hi> whoſe Sepulchre is the <hi>Stocks,</hi> and his Monument a <hi>Pillory.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:55195:51"/>
            <head>The Character of a ſelf-conceited Fellow.</head>
            <p>HE is, I dare not ſay a Man, nor Boy; but in the Parentheſis of both; yet he thinks onely a beard is wanting to proclaim his manhood; becauſe he has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up Womens Smocks, he writes <hi>ſumptâ virili togâ,</hi> when indeed his wit is hardly out of the <hi>clouts.</hi> He is an <hi>Ape,</hi> that imitates both, but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the wit of the one, acts naturally the folly of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He thinks himſelf of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:55195:51"/> deep judgement, yet has nothing deep about him, but the pits of his noſe; which makes him boaſt of hills and dales in his own poſſeſſion. He affects two contraries; for he will be a laughing-ſtock to good company, where his higheſt ambition is to be told he talks like an <hi>Apothecary;</hi> or elſe is the <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weather</hi> of children, fools, or <hi>Frenchmen;</hi> who have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Engliſh</hi> enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his nonſenſe, nor to approve his <hi>no-wit;</hi> but paſ it over for jeſts by ignorant laughter. He is an <hi>ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus</hi> to miſlead fools by a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nothing that is in him
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:55195:52"/> or a blazing Star placed in the lower Regions of a <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern;</hi> and a Cup in his brain portends the birth of ſome prodigious Conceit. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate himſelf into good company, he keeps conſtantly in pay a <hi>Regiment</hi> of jeſts and hard words, to ſalute their ears with a volley of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe; which if they be not grac'd with laughter, he is non-ſuited. But being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roabed of this ſtore, he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers them of a Wench; and rather then want imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will turn Pimp. You cannot pleaſe him unleſs you praiſe him; nor praiſe him, unleſs you flatter him, It is
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:55195:52"/> his <hi>ſummuni bonum</hi> to move laughter; and if his <hi>jeſts</hi> will not do it, his <hi>geſture</hi> muſt; if neither, you may laugh at the Jeſtor. He moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly procures friendſhip with ſome <hi>wit,</hi> whom he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns to be the foreman in the peale of laughter; who both to his face, and behind his back, laughs at him. Much he affects to ſpeak ſome Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Language, becauſe in all his Diſcourſe he would over-reach the <hi>capacity</hi> of an <hi>Engliſhman.</hi> He whiſpers <hi>How d'you,</hi> as if 'twere Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in the ears of any new acquaintance, to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thinke he is privie to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:55195:53"/> their ſecrets. He alwaies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts from other mens worth behind their backs; as if he knew by inſtinct others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſed him; and it goes hard if a man wears any clothes, but he will pick a hole in his coat. He hath not exchanged two words with Nature in love (I had almoſt ſaid ſince he was of underſtanding) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe made him ſo low, that he cannot overlook o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens actions; but to help this defect, he hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the faculty of taking the wall of his betters; having nothing in himſelf worth this knowledge; he ſcorns <hi>noſcere ſeipſum.</hi> The <hi>thing</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:55195:53"/> Poeticall wherein he caſts up his ignorance, to make it ſeem of high ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; he writes like the <hi>Egyptian darkneſs,</hi> wherein he ſhews cunning; for when men laugh at his Verſes, he may ſay they laugh at they know not what; and can boaſt of more then any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Poet,</hi> that he writes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove humane apprehenſion. He carries ſuch a deep con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of his own <hi>conceits,</hi> that he thinks no man worthy to underſtand them; nay he is ſuch a nigard, that he grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth himſelf the benefit. The Subject of his Fancy is himſelf; wherein he truly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:55195:54"/> ſhews himſelf <hi>poeticall,</hi> if Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions can do. He miſlikes every man after the firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; nay grows wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his native Countrey, and will travell; and his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and carriage therein, not tongue can expreſs but his own, for he may lie by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. Himſelf is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the limits of my Paper, where my Pen nor can nor will follow him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:55195:54"/>
            <head>The Character of a City Wit.</head>
            <p>HE is a gaudy <hi>Vacuum,</hi> gilded over with a few hard words, which he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines to have a deep mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe his dull ſenſe cannot dive into it; which with much pains he has wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Authors, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Gariſon in a <hi>common place-book,</hi> that he might draw out a Regiment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits when his wit is routed. His Diſcourſe is a Line of Sand, or a compoſition of ſo
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:55195:55"/> many <hi>foot</hi> and <hi>half-words,</hi> which being put together, ſpell <hi>non-ſenſe.</hi> He admits not a word into his Society, under the degree of a <hi>Tetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilable;</hi> and takes all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by meaſure, not weight. He were the only man to be <hi>Minſhew</hi>'s Son, and compoſe another <hi>Dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary</hi> of hard words, had he but wit enough to ſpell them, or learning to tell their <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> Yet he thinks his noſe a <hi>Jacobs Staff,</hi> able to calculate the height of any mans fancy. By his tedious Diſcourſes of <hi>Herauldry,</hi> he would make you believe he were a Gentleman. And to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:55195:55"/> gain Honour, he dares be a Souldier; and hath taken up Arms on his <hi>Signet,</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his little finger; but intends only to fight by the <hi>Heraulds</hi> Book, where his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour will be ſeen by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable hanging, drawing, and quartering of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Coat.</hi> He had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to a <hi>Trumpeters</hi> place, but that he could ſound no Alarm, but his own praiſe. Had he but Poetry, he would out-vaper <hi>Ben;</hi> but he'l not ſpeak a Verſe, leſt they ſhould be taken for children of his own begetting, and known by their <hi>long legs.</hi> Beſides his ſpeeches are ſo maſterleſs,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:55195:56"/> they think it againſt the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject to be chained in a Verſe. In his Arguments his Solutions are more intricate then the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; and that man needs a deep reach that would define his definition. After many <hi>Pleonaſmes</hi> and <hi>Circumlocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> he is delivered at length of a <hi>non-ſequitur;</hi> yet makes no <hi>Concluſion,</hi> for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is endleſs. You may be ſick of a <hi>Conſumption,</hi> and cured before he hath finiſhed a <hi>Complement;</hi> and 'tis a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the <hi>Palſey</hi> in his tongue procure not the <hi>frenzie</hi> in his head. <hi>Shews</hi> he prefers before <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> and eſteems an <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:55195:56"/> in Folio before a poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket <hi>Bible.</hi> He uſeth much to diſcommend himſelf; which we muſt interpret as a praiſe, the clean contrary way; yet rather then loſe a drop of his praiſe, he will lick it up with his own tongue. The way to gain his favour, is neither to underſtand him, nor be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by him; he will then applaud the depth of your judgement; for it is his property to think nothing <hi>deep,</hi> unleſs it be <hi>muddy.</hi> He accounts no man rich in wit, that does not <hi>gingle</hi> with it in every fooles company; he thinks not that a mans Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe may be full, whoſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:55195:57"/> Shop is empty; and a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Learning in that head, where there is no channell in the tongue. He would fain be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> for he is very <hi>peripateticall;</hi> and becauſe his wit is bald, he Periwigs it with ſtolne <hi>Comings,</hi> which he calls his own, becauſe he bought them, and ſaith he ſtudied hard for them; but it was onely to remember them; and if by chance any word do put out his head in company, and is not concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he'l ſwear 'tis an <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conceit.</hi> Becauſe he is tall, he thinks his fancy is predominant, and therefore is apt to inſult over any ſhort
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:55195:57"/> man, though he hath more underſtanding. He thinks every man barren of Worth, that has not his tongue tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with ſelfe-praiſe; and thoſe unacquainted with wit, that have not their fancies writ in their faces, perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to every Reader. He is mighty glad if he be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with a fool, and thinks him his foyle, though indeed he be his Looking-glaſs. From the ruines of good Buildings he erects the <hi>Babels</hi> of his own conceit, and enriches his brain; which indeed is no other but a confuſion of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, where ſcarce one ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable underſtands another.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:55195:58"/> In the <hi>Church</hi> we muſt look for him in the higheſt Pew; but I am loth to ſtay his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out, leſt he offend my ſtomack with ſome tedious Paraphraſe upon the Sermon; but there I leave him praying againſt a handſom Wife, leſt he be made a Cuckold; and againſt a witty Companion, leſt he be made a Coxſcomb.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:55195:58"/>
            <head>The Character of a Humouriſt.</head>
            <p>HIs principall humour ſhall be my excuſe; that is, <hi>inconſtancy;</hi> 'tis hard to draw his Picture, that will not ſettle his countenance; therefore expect it rather in a <hi>Landskip</hi> then <hi>Statua.</hi> He is unſetled both in his actions and opinions; which ſhews his <hi>fancy</hi> to predominate in him, rather then <hi>judgement;</hi> yet can it not be denied, but that he is maſter of a ſound
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:55195:59"/> judgement, but he makes others, not himſelf the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of it; being better able to inform others, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his life; and more able to <hi>declaim</hi> againſt others vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then <hi>reclaim</hi> his own. His anger is more active then hot, rather ſcorching then burning; ſoon kindled, and as ſoon quencht. And though that man muſt needs make a ſtrange combuſtion in the State of his ſoul, that upon the landing of every <hi>Cockboat</hi> ſets the <hi>Beacons</hi> on fire; yet becauſe his Reaſon ſtands Centinell, 'tis rather a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then a mutiny. <hi>Vertue</hi> he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:55195:59"/> more gazeth after then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows; or if he do follow, it is rather with his tongue then feet; chooſing to talk with her ſooner then walke after her; and prefers a dram of <hi>Theoricks</hi> before a pound of Practicks. At the <hi>Game</hi> of unlawfull Pleaſures he had rather be an <hi>Actor</hi> then a <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator;</hi> ſeldom forſaking them till teeth like he be forced to drop off through too much ſatiety. Melancholy he will be in the midſt of <hi>mirth;</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly when he and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (for they are ſtrangers) they are excellent company.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:55195:60"/> 
               <hi>Venus</hi> he eſteems above all the ſeven Planets; but had rather worſhip her in a <hi>Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-houſe</hi> then in any of the twelve <hi>Celeſtiall Signes.</hi> In his Materials he is a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; but Fortune hath caſt him in the <hi>City</hi> Mould. No doubt but age will reclaim his unſtay'dneſs; 'tis no great fault in a young Horſe to uſe unreaſonable mounting. To his friends he is rather for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall then reall; apt to truſt them with his perſon, not ſecrets. In a falling out of two friends, he will rather ſide with one, then bring both agreed; which is an
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:55195:60"/> 
               <hi>Index</hi> of ſome indiſcretion; thereby he being ſure of two friends, to make one his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. He is no ſtranger to <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> which is Muſick in words; nor to Muſick, which is Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in ſound; yet rather makes them his Sauce then Meat. For <hi>Logick,</hi> which gives Speech ſubſtance; or <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> which gives it Beauty; or <hi>Grammar,</hi> which gives a Tongue to Speech it ſelf; he has only ta'ne a <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory</hi> view of the firſt of the three; but has ruminated on the two laſt. But leſt I make my Garment to big for the Body which I took meaſure
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:55195:61"/> of; and being ſomething in haſte, I conclude with his own Proverb, <hi>By—I cannot ſtay.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:55195:61"/>
            <head>The Character of a FUDLER.</head>
            <p>WE will onely take a curſory view of him as he is in <hi>company,</hi> being not yet ſo unhappy to know him farther; but we may gueſs at the bulk of <hi>Hercules</hi> by his foot. He is a confuſed lump moulded when Nature did all things in the dark; a <hi>Cub</hi> of the <hi>Chaos</hi> not lick'd into form, rowled from <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> to <hi>Tavern</hi> onely to be drunk and laught at; where
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:55195:62"/> he <hi>grunts</hi> out words as ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhap'd and groſs as his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and if his ſpeeches do chance to quarrell, you muſt take them as they fall out. His body is built like <hi>Babel,</hi> but never with an intent to reach Heaven; the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were confounded, and put Morter where Gold ſhould be. His ordinary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is only ſcurrility and profaneſs in a miſcellany, boyled together in huge quantities of <hi>Sack,</hi> which he carves to his friends as prime Dainties. Rather then his <hi>Jeſts</hi> ſhall want fire, he will light them at Gods Altar;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:55195:62"/> and though a Conceit grow on the Banks of <hi>Hell,</hi> he will adventure to fetch it; not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to gain his Conceit, though he loſe his ſoul. In company he monopolizeth all the Diſcourſe to himſelf; not regarding if his <hi>tongue</hi> keep on a gallop before, how far his <hi>underſtanding</hi> loyters behind. Sometimes his Wit ſtumbles on a Jeſt, as he that ſhoots thick, ſometimes may hit; and then you will do him a great diſcourteſie, if you do not laugh; but the main body of his Diſcourſe is a <hi>Wild-gooſe chaſe</hi> after ſome printed wit, which he
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:55195:63"/> cannot catch. When he ſpeaks, 'tis not the motion of his tongue, but the rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his brains; and 'tis worth our wonder, that his belly ſhould be ſo full, and head ſo empty; but the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the one is the empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the other. His belly, like the great Fiſh, eats up all the reſt of his limbs, yet his wit is as <hi>fat</hi> as that. He has ſpent much time in travell to learn to be an <hi>Aſs;</hi> all that he has ſeen is the <hi>Tun</hi> at <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleburgh,</hi> which he ſtudies to imitate; and all that he hath brought away, is the exact managing of his <hi>Fork</hi> at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:55195:63"/> He walks in the ſtreets like a Rundlet of Sack on two poſts; and where'ere he goes, he carries a fool with him. His ſtudy is old Jeſts and Tales; his recreation, Drinking; and his main oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation is Wenching. But I fear I have been too long in his company; by this time he is drunk, 'tis time to leave him leſt he ſpue in our faces.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="character">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:55195:64"/>
            <head>A Solicitor</head>
            <p>IS one of the blades of <hi>Corn</hi> that ſprings from the <hi>Ilian</hi> ruines, whoſe <hi>ears</hi> grow up for the Harveſt of a <hi>Pilory.</hi> His Profeſſion is originally like a <hi>Cuckow,</hi> from the <hi>Neſt</hi> of another <hi>Trade;</hi> where he has learned wrangling and knavery enough in his own <hi>Cauſes</hi> to ſpoil another mans. With the ſweetned <hi>Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> of <hi>City fraud</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds himſelf (though ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple enough) for any villany.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:55195:64"/> He is truly ſaid to <hi>follow a Cauſe;</hi> but a ſmall Bribe will <hi>lame</hi> him ſo, that he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come near it. He is one of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, that fires all about him; but that his fire is generally in his <hi>noſe,</hi> as well as his <hi>tail.</hi> His ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo low, not to have his Chamber in an Innes of Court, but in an Ale-houſe of the City; a Tavern is his <hi>form,</hi> and licking of Pots his <hi>Law.</hi> Moſt of his Actions are <hi>Aſſaults,</hi> or <hi>Slanders;</hi> which are broach'd where his Ale is, in a <hi>Cellar;</hi> and after a long circumſtance, <hi>center</hi> themſelves where they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:55195:65"/> where his fooliſh Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, being weary of his fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs endleſs Suit, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the idle expence of his Money for an imaginary <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>num,</hi> called <hi>getting the day;</hi> like the <hi>Chymiſt,</hi> that blows away his <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Lungs,</hi> for that <hi>Fools</hi> (rather then <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers)</hi> Stone; do's by his wholſom advice, when his Money is ſpent, refer his Suit to <hi>Arbitrators</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires;</hi> whoſe Verdict is, after long debate, A Supper for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, at the equall charge of both Parties; That both muſt be ſony for what they have done (as they have
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:55195:65"/> good cauſe) and ſit down by their loſſes. He ſeldom gets any conſiderable prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but among <hi>Fiſh-wives</hi> or <hi>Watermen,</hi> or in a <hi>Countrey Village,</hi> where all ſtand in awe of him, and ſlander him with the Title of <hi>Maſter Lawyer. Ignorance</hi> and <hi>beggary</hi> makes him reſolute, that he dares thruſt his head into any em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. At laſt, having run through the <hi>Zodiack</hi> of all Courts, if he ſcape the preferment of the Gallows, he caſts Anchor in a Goal, or a Bridewell; and there we leave him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
